<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some farther considerations concerning alkaly and acid, by way of appendix to a late essay Wherein the terms are made clear, and the natures of them both more fully explained: together with an answer to the objections that have been raised against some things contained in the said essay. By John Colbatch, physician.</title>
            <title>Physico-medical essay, concerning alkaly and acid. Appendix</title>
            <author>Colbatch, John, Sir, 1670-1729.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204393</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896885</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896885</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135371</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80062)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2461:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some farther considerations concerning alkaly and acid, by way of appendix to a late essay Wherein the terms are made clear, and the natures of them both more fully explained: together with an answer to the objections that have been raised against some things contained in the said essay. By John Colbatch, physician.</title>
                  <title>Physico-medical essay, concerning alkaly and acid. Appendix</title>
                  <author>Colbatch, John, Sir, 1670-1729.</author>
                  <author>Colbatch, John, Sir, 1670-1729. physico-medical essay, concerning alkaly and acid.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Dan. Brown, at the Black Swan and Bible without Temple-Bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A late essay = A physico-medical essay, concerning alkaly and acid (Wing C5003 et seq.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chemistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135371:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135371:1"/>
            <p> Some Farther CONSIDERATIONS Concerning ALKALY and ACID, By Way of APPENDIX To a late ESSAY.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The <hi>Terms</hi> are made Clear, and the <hi>Natures</hi> of them Both more fully Explained: Together with an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Objections</hi> that have been raiſed againſt ſome Things contained in the ſaid <hi>Eſſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Colbatch, <hi>Phyſician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Dan. Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1696.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135371:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135371:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Learned and Ingenious Dr. <hi>Edward Baynard,</hi> Fellow of the College of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Civil and Gentleman-like Treatment I met with the firſt time I ſaw you, and the many Favours I have received from you ſince I have been honoured with your more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Acquaintance, emboldens me to proſtrate this Trifle at your
<pb facs="tcp:135371:3"/> Feet; not pretending thereby to merit any thing from you, but as a juſt Acknowledgment of the many Obligations I lye under. It would be a Wrong to you for me to ſpeak any thing in your Praiſe, your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits being better known, than I am able to repreſent them. It was you, SIR, who were (for ought I know) the moſt early Cultivator of the Doctrine of <hi>Acids</hi> in the Cure of Diſeaſes, in this Nation; and the Succeſs you have had in your Practice ſufficiently makes it appear, that you very well underſtood what you went about, when you durſt contend with the whole World, by treading in a New Path to Aid and Succor Life, which few Phyſicians ever went before. <hi>Macte!</hi> SIR, in ſo Great a Work as in Saving from the Grave; ſo ſhall the Name of <hi>Baynard</hi> not be known to the Widow, nor the Cries of the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs entail Vengeance on your Houſe. And would your Multiplicity of
<pb facs="tcp:135371:3"/> Buſineſs but permit you to collect your own Obſervations, and make them Publick, I am ſure the Mouths of all your Oppoſers would be for ever ſtopp'd, and their Errors cured by your Healing Hand; for I know your Charity extends to Lunacy, as well as other Diſeaſes: For none but the Moon-ſick can doubt ſo known and clear a Truth, as are the daily and moſt apparent Cures done by (the Happy Diſcovery of) the Uſe of <hi>Acids.</hi> 'Tis well known, SIR, that Nature and Art has ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arm'd you for any Enemy, if ſuch there are; tho your Condonable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is like the Sun, which ſhines even upon the Curs that bark at him. Your Pardon, SIR, for this Trouble, and I doubt not but from you to meet with a Generous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and Protection; and if Dr. <hi>Baynard</hi> eſpouſe my Cauſe, I care not who is againſt me. I aſſure you I bring no common Inclinations to ſerve you; neither would I by
<pb facs="tcp:135371:4"/> ordinary Teſtimonies expreſs that Paſſion wherewith I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and moſt Devoted Servant, <hi>JOHN COLBATCH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:135371:4"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have ſo enquired into the Cauſes of Diſeaſes, as to be altogether certain of the truth of the <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis</hi> I have already advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and am now, in ſome meaſure, endeavouring to confirm: But I don't at all pretend to have arrived to ſo much Certainty as that by the Methods I take, to make People Immortal, and that no Perſon ſhall die with whom I am concerned, which is what I believe ſome People have expected from me. But, for my Part, I ſhall always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſubmit to, and have reſpects for the Providence of the Almighty, who alone is the Author and Diſpoſer
<pb facs="tcp:135371:5"/> of our Lives; and who by the mouth of an Inſpired Writer, has declared, That our days are determined; and beyond the Limitation, ſet by that wiſe Author of Nature, we cannot paſs; it being altogether impoſſible for Creatures to contend with their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or to extend the Time that he hath limited.</p>
            <p>Phyſicians are, of all men, without doubt, the moſt unhappy; People, in their Extremities, looking upon them as their Saviours and Deliverers; yet after all, they having done as much as 'twas in the power of man to do, having in all reſpects acquitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the utmoſt fidelity and diligence, if their Patients die, their appointed time being come, and the number of their days, alotted them by the Almighty, being expired; yet the Friends and Relations of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deceaſed, ſeldom fail to charge them in one reſpect or other, though inſtead of being blamed, the Phyſician has
<pb facs="tcp:135371:5"/> deſerved their utmoſt Favour and Eſteem.</p>
            <p>By what I have ſaid, I would not be ſo underſtood, That I am ſo far a <hi>Predeſtinarian,</hi> as to believe that Peoples Lives are not frequently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed by the uſe of fit and proper Medicines: For if it were not ſo, why ſhould the wiſe Creator have been at ſo much trouble, in providing ſuch a vaſt number of Medicines, in the Animal, Vegetable, and Mineral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms? if he did not by them deſign a real ſervice to Mankind in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</p>
            <p>God generally gives a Bleſſing to proper means, it not being uſual for him to work Miracles every day. He teaches the Plowman how to plow his Ground, and the Seedſman to ſowe his Seed; but the Plowman, inſtead of a Plow, muſt not uſe a Harrow; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt the Seedſman expect to reap Wheat, if he ſowes Barley: So it is in the practice of Phyſick, he that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects ſucceſs in his Practice, muſt firſt
<pb facs="tcp:135371:6"/> endeavour rightly to know the Cauſes of Diſeaſes, and then to uſe fit Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and after that, the Event muſt be left to the Bleſſing of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <p>The Plowman may plow his ground aright, and the Seedſman ſowe his Seed in due ſeaſon, and after all is done they may reap no Crop: ſo the Phyſician may have an exact know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Cauſes of Diſeaſes, and may uſe the moſt fit and proper Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines in the World, and yet at laſt be fruſtrated in his Aim: Which ought to ſhew us what an exact reliance and dependance we ſhould have upon the Bleſſing of God on all our Endeavours, without which, we are like to make but little progreſs in any thing.</p>
            <p>I tread in an unbeaten Path, and therefore cannot ſo happily and eaſily arrive at my Journeys end, as if I had had ſome body or other before, to have chalked out my way for me.</p>
            <p>I hope I ſhall not by theſe my En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, incur the diſpleaſure of any
<pb facs="tcp:135371:6"/> one of thoſe Phyſicians who are of a contrary Judgment to me, they being ſtill left at liberty to uſe their own Methods and Alkalious Medicines: For tho we act upon different Principles, our Ends and Deſigns are the ſame, which are the Cure of Diſeaſes; and if I, after a multitude of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, am convinced that <hi>Acids</hi> are not the Cauſes of Diſeaſes, but, on the contrary, that <hi>Alkalies</hi> are, and upon that ſcore am induced to uſe <hi>Acids</hi> in all or moſt Diſtempers; I don't ſee any reaſon why People ſhould reproach me for it, ſince I have made no Perſonal Reflections upon any one.</p>
            <p>As for the Phyſicians of our own Nation, I have the higheſt Value and Eſteem for them, having generally found them to be Men of greater Learning, and who underſtand the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of their Profeſſion better than any of the Phyſicians I have at all met with abroad.</p>
            <p>As for going again to <hi>Flanders</hi> with the Army, I never deſign that any
<pb facs="tcp:135371:7"/> more, being ſufficiently deterred from it, by the ill Treatment I had there laſt Year, by the means of ſome of my old Friends the Surgeons. And that I may no longer continue at Variance with ſo great a Body of Men, I have ſold the Receipt of my Vulnerary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Tincture, and all the ſaid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines I had by me, to a Gentleman who is better able to diſpoſe of them for the Publick Good of Mankind than I could; and therefore ſhall for the future wholly apply my ſelf to my Practice of Phyſick, in which if I have Succeſs (which I doubt not) I ſhall have buſineſs, maugre all my Enemies Malice.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Villars-ſtreet, York-Buildings <hi>in the</hi> Strand, <date>
                     <hi>Mar. 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
                     </hi> 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135371:7"/>
            <head>Some further CONSIDERATIONS Concerning <hi>Alkaly</hi> and <hi>Acid,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Thought to have ſaid no more upon this Subject, until the Publication of my Hiſtory of Human Blood: But I finding that to be a thing of greater difficulty, and that a much greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Experiments than I at firſt thought of, will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make that Hiſtory
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135371:8"/> compleat in all its Parts; by which means it will be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing longer than I at firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, before that Piece ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the world: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have thought fit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To explain the Terms, or what is meant by <hi>Alkaly,</hi> and what by <hi>Acid;</hi> which I find very many people, who are not Phyſicians, are in great meaſure ignorant of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To explain the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them ſomewhat more fully and clearly than I have yet done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Objections that have been raiſed againſt ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular things contained in my Eſſay.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135371:8"/>
            <p> All which Heads I ſhall han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with as much Brevity and Perſpicuity as poſſibly I can; omitting the more full Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, till the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my Hiſtory of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Blood, which, I hope, will be ready for the Preſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Month of <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall make bold to declare, That I have not Publiſhed this Doctrine of <hi>Alkaly</hi> and <hi>Acid,</hi> out of any deſign of appearing ſingular, or being the Head of a Faction, but out of mere Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Compaſſion to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, my Fellow-Creatures, whoſe deplorable Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under Miſtaken Methods, I have long bewailed; to ſee Phyſick made the Scene of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135371:9"/> Slaughter, and ſo many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Mortals (the helpleſs Sick) ſent daily to their Laſt Homes, as Victims to Error and Ignorance: Whilſt the Learned Preſcriber jogs on in his old miſtaken Alkalious Road; not dreaming (as the Wiſe-Man ſays) <hi>that Death is there, and that his Portion</hi> (I mean the Patient's) <hi>is with the Worms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that I may return to my Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To explain the Terms, or what is meant by <hi>Alkaly,</hi> and what by <hi>Acid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alkaly</hi> derives its Name from the Herb <hi>Kaly,</hi> from the Aſhes of which Herb is extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a large quantity of Salt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135371:9"/> which by the <hi>Venetians</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is much uſed in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Soap and Glaſs; and this Salt they call <hi>Sal Kaly,</hi> and by leaving out the <hi>S Alkaly.</hi> Now the Aſhes of all or moſt Vegetables affording a Salt of the ſame nature with the Aſhes of the Herb <hi>Kaly,</hi> therefore all Lixivial Salts are equivocally called <hi>Alkalies,</hi> and all other things of the ſame nature, whether manifeſtly Saline or not, <hi>Alkalies;</hi> ſuch are Arſnick, and all the Teſtacea, as Pearl, Coral, Crabs-Eyes, Oyſter-Shells, <hi>&amp;c.;</hi> and all Urinous Spirits and Salts, ſuch as Spirit and Salt of Blood, Urine, Harts-horn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſome think, that of theſe <hi>Alkalies</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135371:10"/> are made the famous White Powder, ſo much talk'd of, which kills without a Bounce, and murthers without making a Noiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acid,</hi> I ſuppoſe, did firſt derive its name from <hi>Acaid,</hi> an <hi>Arabian</hi> Word for <hi>Acetum,</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, which is the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and known Acid; and therefore all things of the ſame Taſte and Nature with Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, <hi>Acids;</hi> ſuch are the Jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of moſt Fruits and Plants in their Natural ſtate, and unfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; though all fermented Vegetable Juices do after fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation retain ſomething of their priſtine Acidity, though not in ſo eminent a degree: But every body knows that all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135371:10"/> fermented Juices, ſuch as all ſorts of Wine, Ale, Beer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let them be preſerved with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much care, will at laſt return to their priſtine ſtate of Acidity. All Metaline Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs ate to be ranged amongſt the Number of Acids, they being nothing but a Congeſtion of Acid Particles. I may likewiſe without preſumption reckon all ſorts of Balſoms and Pinquedinous and Oleaginous Subſtances, amongſt the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Acids; by reaſon that in the moſt bare and ſimple Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, they afford large quantities of Acid Subſtances, but nothing that is Alkalious. Bread alſo, that is, not without reaſon accounted the Staff of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135371:11"/> Life, affords alſo by Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a large quantity of an Acid Subſtance, which is no deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Menſtruum. Sugar, which though in its Taſte ſeems to be nothing leſs than an Acid, yet by a Philoſophical Management appears to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Congeſtion of Acid Particles.</p>
            <p>Thus for the preſent I think I have given a ſufficient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what I mean by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaly,</hi> and what by <hi>Acid;</hi> and alſo what things are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Alkalies,</hi> and what <hi>Acids.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome things which ſeem to be of a mixt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture between Alkaly and Acid, which things we call Neutrals.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135371:11"/> Now thoſe things of this Tribe which afford by much a greater quantity of Acid Subſtances than Alkalious ones, I ſtick not to call <hi>Acids,</hi> becauſe the Acid predominates; and thoſe that afford by much a greater quantity of Alkalious than A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid Subſtances, I call <hi>Alkalies.</hi> Though in a more ſtrict ſenſe they deſerve rather to be called either Sub-Acid Alkalies, or Sub-Alkaline Acids, according as either the one or the other predominates.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now proceed to my <hi>Second</hi> thing, which is, To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Nature of Alkalies and Acids more fully and clearly than I have yet done.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:135371:12"/>
            <p> For the well Performance of which Task, I ſhall compare the Operation of them both upon Human Bodies, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally taken, and externally applied.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with <hi>Sal Kaly,</hi> which is the Standard of Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and compare that with Vinegar the Standard of Acids.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sal Kaly,</hi> and ſo all Lixivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Vegetable Salts, as Salt of Wormwood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied outwardly to the bare Skin, ſcorcheth and burneth the ſame, all one as if a Red Hot Iron were actually applied to it, cauſing an Eſcar, which falling off, an Ulcer follows: Nay, indeed there is ſcarce any other Cauſtick uſed, than
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135371:12"/> a Lixivium of <hi>Sal Kaly,</hi> which is what the Chyrurgeons call Capital or Strong Soap-Lees, evaporated to Drineſs. The ſame being taken inwardly, without being greatly diluted by ſome Aqueous Vehicle, in moſt people cauſeth enormous Vomitings, which I my ſelf have formerly experienced; and if it be never ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, if it doth not excite Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitings, it rarely fails of either depraving, palling, or totally deſtroying the Appetite: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, being conveyed into the Blood, by breaking its Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bules and ſpoiling of its Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it cauſeth either Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, Rheumatiſms, Sciatica's, Conſumptions, Gout, Palſies,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135371:13"/> or ſome other of the fatal Tribe of Chronical Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Now I have ſhewn what <hi>Sal Kaly,</hi> and the reſt of the Tribe of Vegetable Lixivious Salts will do; in the next place let's ſee what effects even com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon plain Vinegar, which is the ſtandard of Acids, will have, being externally uſed, and internally taken.</p>
            <p>It is well known, that Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar being externally applied, is of extraordinary uſe in a great many ſorts of Inflamations, of ſingular uſe in an <hi>Eriſipelas,</hi> or St. <hi>Anthony</hi>'s Fire. Cloaths being dipp'd in it, and applied to the Forehead and Temples, to the Wriſts, the Stomach, and bottoms of the Feet, I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135371:13"/> found to be of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary uſe in ſome very burning Feavers: I have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe my ſelf (before I had found out a more certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy) ſometimes made uſe of it with good ſucceſs in great Bleedings at the Noſe, by dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Spunge in good ſtrong Vinegar, and applying it to the Scrotum. I have alſo known it with good ſucceſs to have been made uſe of by poor people, in ſtinking old Ulcers. From all which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that being externally applied, it's no Cauſtick, and will make no Ulcer, but on the contrary, will cure Ulcers, eaſe Pain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135371:14"/>
            <p> Now we have ſeen ſome of its good Effects, being exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally applied; let's ſee what it will do being internally taken.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an Account given of it by the Ingenious Dr. <hi>Baynard:</hi> He ſays that he was called in to a Perſon who had a Total Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Urine, under which he had laboured ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time, and that ſeveral things had in vain been given him; he immediately gave him a large Draught of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, which ſoon made him to Piſs freely; and by repeating of it two or three times, he was perfectly freed from his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition. The Doctor has given an account of this in one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135371:14"/> of the Philoſophical Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but I have not read it, neither have I time at preſent to look over thoſe Papers. I think alſo he has told me, that the ſame thing he has done with the ſame plain Medicine two or three times. He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe gave me ſeveral Inſtances of many Perſons in moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Fevers, who have been preſently cured by drinking large Draughts of <hi>Atterpool</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter well acidulated.</p>
            <p>I am alſo moſt creditably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, That Dr. <hi>Bently,</hi> a late famous Phyſician in <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> who lived to almoſt a Hundred Years of Age, had ſuch wonderful Succeſs in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that he acquir'd the Name
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135371:15"/> of the <hi>Feaver-Doctor,</hi> and that his Medicine was nothing elſe but the Decoction of a certain Herb well acidulated with the Spirit of—; a Noble Acid, which I am obliged not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal.</p>
            <p>A Worthy Lady, whoſe Name I muſt not mention, has aſſured me, That ſhe has brought in the uſe of Vinegar or Verjuice Poſſet-drink, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt her poor Neighbours in the Countrey where ſhe lives, in the Small-Pox; and where that has been uſed from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſhe has ſcarce obſerv'd any one to dye or be disfigur'd; which is agreeable to what I obſerve in my Eſſay, <hi>p.</hi> 24.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:135371:15"/>
            <p> I have likewiſe frequently obſerved, that three or four Spoonfuls of Vinegar, will immediately check the moſt violent Vomitings, occaſioned by the taking of ſome harſh Antimonial Medicines.</p>
            <p>A great many other good qualities hath ſimple Vinegar internally taken, and external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied (beſides its being a good Menſtruum) that I think not fit here to enumerate.</p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall do will be to compare <hi>Arſnick,</hi> as the higheſt and moſt exalted <hi>Alkaly,</hi> with <hi>Oyl of Vitriol,</hi> the moſt exalted <hi>Acid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the external uſe of <hi>Arſnick,</hi> I know nothing of it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135371:16"/> experimentally; but it being a thing of that pernicious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence internally taken, I ſuppoſe it can have no very friendly operation externally applied.</p>
            <p>Internally taken, it cauſeth the moſt enormous Vomitings and Convulſions of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, Cold Sweats, Palpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Heart, Swoonings, moſt violent Thirſt, and in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, ſeems to be a direct Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Life, which in a ſhort time it fails not to deſtroy. All which effects it will not fail to have, given in never ſo ſmall a quantity. And all thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who have been ſo vain as to pretend to correct the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Venomous Quality of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135371:16"/> 
               <hi>Arſnick,</hi> ſo as to convert it into a good and ſafe Medicine, have attempted it only by the means of <hi>Acid</hi> Salts, ſuch as Sea-Salt, Nitre, Tartar, Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein I cannot tell whether any man hath yet been ſo happy as to ſucceed.</p>
            <p>To prove <hi>Arſnick</hi> to be an <hi>Alkaly,</hi> and as ſuch is the Cauſe of all thoſe dreadful Symptoms that attend thoſe people who are ſo unhappy as to take it, I ſhall inſert a Relation made to me by Mr. <hi>Payne</hi> an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary of <hi>Brandford,</hi> on <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> Feb. 16. which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:</p>
            <p>A certain Young Woman of <hi>Brandford</hi> having taken a very
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135371:17"/> large quantity of <hi>Arſnick</hi> (as he told me, an Ounce) ſhe was immediately attended with all the moſt violent Symptoms imaginable; upon which Dr. <hi>Morris</hi> was called in, who gave her large Quantities of Sallad Oyl, the uſual Remedy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in the leaſt abating the Symptoms: Upon which he ordered them to procure a large quantity of Lemmons, and to preſs the Juice out of them, of which Juice he plentifully gave her, which ſoon took off and abated thoſe imminent and direful Symptoms which inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably threaten'd Death; though the Operation of the <hi>Acid</hi> might be ſomewhat impeded, through the quantity of Oyl ſhe had taken before.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135371:17"/>
            <p> But to return to my Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is to ſee what are the Effects of <hi>Oyl of Vitriol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs the Acid Particles of <hi>Oyl of Vitriol</hi> are ſo concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated, as to make it unfit to be externally applied, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally taken, of it ſelf; but being diluted in any proper Vehicle, is a Medicine ſecond to none that I know of. A few Drops in Canary, given to the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Children who are troubled with Worms, ſeldom or never fails of having the deſired ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. It being mixed with Honey of Roſes, is one of the beſt Medicines that perhaps is known, for the Scurvy in the Gums, breeding Fleſh where it it is wanting, and faſtening the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135371:18"/> Teeth. Being mixed with Spring-Water and Brandy, of each equal parts, to a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Acidity, is no deſpicable Medicine in giving eaſe in the moſt Tormenting Pains of the Gout, the Part being foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it Night and Morning. I may be almoſt poſitive, that the Medicine uſed by the Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious <hi>Swiſs</hi> Gentlemen who now reſide in this City, and are become ſo deſervedly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, particularly for the Cure of Sir <hi>Robert Howard,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Mixture of <hi>Oyl of Vitriol</hi> with a certain Oleagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Body, in due proportion. The ſame Medicine is alſo uſed and ſold by Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet:</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:135371:18"/> Which Medicine rarely fails gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving immediate Eaſe in the moſt Tormenting Pains of the Gout. Which is a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Truth of what I have ſaid in my Eſſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gout, wherein I aſſert, that it is not from any Acidity in the Blood that the Gout is occaſioned, but from Particles of a quite contrary nature, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Alkalious ones; as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and evidently appears by Analyzing the Chalky Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance contained in the Nodes.</p>
            <p>A better general Medicine than <hi>Oyl of Vitriol</hi> is ſcarce known in moſt continued Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, any ſmall Liquors, as Barley-Water, Small-Beer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:135371:19"/> being well impregnated with it, and drank freely.</p>
            <p>The following Mixture is a very noble Medicine in that painful Diſtemper the Stone in the Kidneys.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Take of Oyl of Bitter-Almonds one Ounce, Oyl of Vitriol Two Drams, Oyl of Saſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fras a Scruple, mix them very well, then add Spirit of Wine rectified three Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, digeſt two or three days in a gentle heat. The Doſe is a ſmall Sweetmeat Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Old-Hock, or Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Juniper-Berries, once in four hours during the Paroxiſm.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:135371:19"/>
               <p> Given for a Month or Six Weeks in an Infuſion of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender Flowers, is an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Medicine in Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I could mention a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Caſes more in which this Medicine is of ſingular uſe; but in ſo doing I ſhould ſwell this Appendix to too great a bulk.</p>
            <p>I ſhall next compare the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacea, ſuch as Pearl, Coral, Crabs-Eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with natural Balſoms and Gums, ſuch as Balm of <hi>Gilead, Tolu, Peru,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gum Ammoniacum, Galbanum,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As for Pearl, Coral, and Crabs Eyes, I know not that they are of any uſe at all, being
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135371:20"/> externally applied; and being internally taken, no body that I know of pretends that they are uſeful any further than to abſorbe the Acidity of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, where people labour under any Indiſpoſition that is attended with an Acidity there. But they are ſo far from being uſeful in that caſe, that I have ſcarce known them uſeful to any one that has taken them upon that ſcore: And in any other caſe they have not the leaſt ſhew of being at all uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but frequently do a great deal of miſchief, as I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in my Eſſay upon the Small-Pox, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here give me leave to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a ſhort Caſe related to me
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135371:20"/> by my worthy Friend Dr. <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> pertinent to this place.</p>
            <p>A Merchant's Wife of ſome Eminence in the City of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol,</hi> labouring under a decayed Stomach, was reduced to ſuch Weakneſs as not able to go, vomiting all ſhe took: Her Phyſicians ſuppoſing her Blood abounded with Acids, had from time to time loaded her weak Stomach with the whole Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of the Alkalious Kingdom, keeping their old Circle, from the Teſtacea to the Volatile Alkalies, and from thence to the Teſtacea again; and at laſt ſhe was perfectly cured with ſome few Doſes of the <hi>Gas Sulphuris,</hi> given in the <hi>Bath-</hi>Waters
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135371:21"/> cold, twice or thrice a day.</p>
            <p>As for Balſams, if I ſhould take upon me to deſcribe their Excellencies, it would be more fit for a large Volume than to take any room in the Appendix to a ſmall Eſſay. What a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Medicine is Balm of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead</hi> in many caſes? The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of which is ſuch, that God by the mouth of an Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Writer, by way of Alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when his people were in a calamitous Condition, cries out, <hi>Is there no Balm in Gilead? Are there no Phyſicians there</hi> (to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it)? <hi>Why then is not the wound of the daughter of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple healed?</hi> What a Noble Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is Ammoniacum in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135371:21"/> moſt deplorable Aſtma's? the Spirit diſtilled from which, and an equal quantity of Verdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe, in a naked Fire, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be as Noble a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine as ever was uſed; nay, all the Gums and Balſams freed from their Ramous, Viſcous parts by Diſtillation, become much better Medicines than when they are in their Natural ſtate.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſams, for fear I outrun my bounds; but ſhall proceed to anſwer ſome Objections raiſed againſt what I have ſaid in ſome parts of my Eſſay.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="objection" n="1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. You ſay that the Scurvey is occaſioned by too
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135371:22"/> great a quantity of <hi>Alkalious</hi> Particles in the Blood, and is only cured by <hi>Acids.</hi> How comes it to paſs that thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that live upon nothing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt but highly-ſalted Meat, are more troubled with the Scurvey than other people, when you own Sea-Salt to be an <hi>Acid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I own that Seamen and People who live by the Sea ſide in Marſhy Grounds, who for the moſt part live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Salt Meat and Fiſh, are more troubled with the Scurvey than other people: But this does not proceed from their eating a larger quantity of Salt than other people, but from their eating more Fleſh and Fiſh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135371:22"/> than other people do, which abound with <hi>Alkalious</hi> Particles, and from the moiſtneſs of the Air about them, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders their free Perſpiration. As for the Sea-Salt which is in great quantities mix'd with their Food, that is all or moſt part of it ſoon carried off by Urine, and with it ſome of the Alkalious ones alſo, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by framing an Armoniack Salt, which it is well known the Urine of ſuch Perſons abounds with: Now what we call <hi>Sal Armoniac,</hi> is only a mixture of Volatile <hi>Alkaly</hi> and Sea-Salt. But the Pores being ſhut by reaſon of the moiſture of the Ambient Air, the Volatile <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaly</hi> which ſhould be diſcharged
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135371:23"/> either by inſenſible Tranſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Sweating, being pent in, cauſes all the Symptoms complained of by thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. To confirm the truth of which, it is well known, that Seamen at Sea, or thoſe people who live in Marſhy Grounds, will ſcarce be made to Sweat by the moſt violent Labour. Now all people who have been ſo curious as to taſte Sweat, do very well know, that it hath an <hi>Alkalious,</hi> and not an <hi>Acid</hi> Taſte; ſo that Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or free Tranſpiration being hindered, the Blood muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily abound with too great a quantity of <hi>Alkalious</hi> Particles; all thoſe that ſhould have been diſcharged by the Cutaneous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135371:23"/> Glands, being kept in it. And ſo I hope this Objection is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="objection" n="2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. In your Eſſay, <hi>Page</hi> 80. you do allow that <hi>Acids</hi> in ſome Diſtempets do exorbitantly abound in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach: Now how comes it to paſs, that there being ſo great a quantity of <hi>Acid</hi> in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, that the Blood and other Juices ſhould be deſtitute of Acidity; there being no other way to convey any thing into the Blood or Juices, but through the Stomach; and therefore whatever the Stomach abounds with, one would think muſt neceſſarily be imparted to the Blood and other Juices?</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:135371:24"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have before obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Nov. Lum. Chyr.</hi> pag. 3, 4. That there is no Innate Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Stomach, but that the Menſtruum made uſe of to diſſolve our Food, and to turn it into a Nutritious Juice, is the Liquor that by chewing of our Meat is ſqueezed out of the Glands of the Mouth, and parts adjacent, which by nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Experiments does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be an <hi>Acid.</hi> Nay, all or moſt of the Noble Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruums I know of, either in the Animal, Vegetable, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Kingdoms, are <hi>Acids.</hi> Now the Food being conveyed into the Stomach, and mixed with the Volatile <hi>Acid</hi> Liquor of the Glands of the Mouth,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135371:24"/> is by the means of the ſaid Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile <hi>Acid</hi> Liquor diſſolved, and turned into a Subſtance fit for the Nutrition of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; a ſtate of Health being ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>It is very well known, that few people are troubled with an Acidity in their Stomachs, but thoſe who uſe very little exerciſe, or whoſe Buſineſs diſpoſes them to a Sedentary Life, and by this means the Chyle when made, for want of Motion and Exerciſe, the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the Stomach alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt their Tone, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come laxe, is not ſoon enough carried out of the Stomach, and lying there too long, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of it is turned into a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135371:25"/> Subſtance like unto the Ferment which at firſt diſſolved it: All people who know the nature of Ferments, will readily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough agree with me in this, That it is the nature of them to endeavour the Change of thoſe things they are mixed with, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own nature.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="objection" n="3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. But ſome will ſay, We can agree with you in what you have ſaid hitherto; but how will you do to clear your ſelf of your own ſeeming Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, which is, That this <hi>Acid</hi> Subſtance ſhall be kept from being conveyed into the Blood, and ſo being the only Cauſe of many Diſeaſes?</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:135371:25"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have always obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That thoſe people who complain of an extraordinary Acidity in their Stomach,</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, They make Water often, and in large quantities.</item>
               <item>Secondly, They are very Lean. And</item>
               <item>Thirdly, They are (for the moſt part) very Coſtive.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All which Symptoms I ſhall endeavour to prove are occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned for want of the <hi>Acid</hi> Subſtance contained in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, being conveyed into the Blood.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt Head, Why people who complain of an Acidity in their Stomachs, make more Water than thoſe who are deſtitute of it; the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135371:26"/> Reaſon I judge to be as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:</p>
            <p>The ſolid Food they eat, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being converted into a Viſcid, White Liquor, we call Chyle only, by means of too great a quantity of <hi>Acid</hi> is over-attenuated, and converted into a Thin Limpid Subſtance, and that in a ſhort time; which Thin Subſtance, by means of the Liver preſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stomach, inſtead of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into the Small Guts through the <hi>Pylorus,</hi> is ſqueezed into certain Veſſels which paſs from the bottom of the Stomach to the Kidneys, and ſo is carried off by Urine.</p>
            <p>To prove that there are ſuch Veſſels which paſs immediately
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135371:26"/> from the bottom of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach to the Kidneys, I ſhall tranſcribe a Paſſage out of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus</hi>'s <hi>Encyclopedia Med.</hi> pag. 359, 360. ſpeaking of the parts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the Dropſy.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe (ſays he) that Liquid Subſtances may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed from the Stomach through the <hi>Omentum</hi> or Cawl, to the Kidneys; hence it is thoſe Animals who have no Cawl, make no Water, as may be ſeen in Birds and Fiſhes. For the Confirmation of which Opinion, I have diſſected ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Animals, always taking care before the Operation to gorge them with large quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of clear Water, afterwards have diſſected them alive: I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135371:27"/> have found the Stomach as yet diſtended with the Water, but preſſing the Veſſels of the Cawl which lead towards the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, which being covered over with Fat like unto the Milky Veins, were to my no little ſatisfaction very Turgid: And foraſmuch as in a living Body the Pores of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and other Paſſages are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways more open than in dead ones, where all things are flaggy, and fall together, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Tranſmutation is not at all to be wonder'd at: And, which is worth taking notice of, in thoſe Hydropical People I have opened, I have always found the Cawl either Putrid, Torn, or full of Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135371:27"/> The following Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has alſo much confirmed me in my Opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That there are Veſſels to convey Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Subſtances from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, through the Veſſels of the Cawl to the Kidneys: Not long ſince, an experienced <hi>Herniotomiſt</hi> or Cutter of Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of <hi>Hanover,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>Wedling,</hi> by Section cured a certain Perſon of an Omental Rupture; and becauſe a part of the Cawl was alſo cut away, the Patient, who is yet alive, does greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of a difficulty in making Water; and if at any time he drinks any large quantity, he perceives a very great Weight and Pain about his Stomach,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135371:28"/> and is always looſe; hence, in my conjecture, ſome Veſſels which carry the Urine right on to the Emulgents, were cut, by which means all the Drink he drank was carried into the <hi>Duodenum,</hi> and ſo hinders the Fermentation that is there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and makes all the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres laxe. From all which may be proved, that all we drink, and of conſequence all other Subſtances made very liquid in the Stomach, do not paſs through the Inteſtines to the Lacteal Veins, and from thence through the Thoractuck Duct to the Heart, becauſe the <hi>Pylorus</hi> is reflex to the Stomach, leſt the Liquid Subſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it ſhould ſlide out:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135371:28"/> It is therefore certain that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Subſtances lying at the bottom of the Stomach, do paſs through it in that part which is joined to the Cawl; and if theſe Veſſels, or the Cawl it ſelf are either lacerated, broken, putrified, or obſtructed with Oedematous Tumors, it neceſſarily follows that the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Subſtances contained in the Stomach muſt be let fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cavity of the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> and ſo a Dropſy is cauſed. But being free from any ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, Liquid Subſtances muſt freely paſs through them to the Kidneys, and ſo to the Bladder. I could cite other Authorities, beſides my own Obſervations, as Sir <hi>George Ent, Charlton,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:135371:29"/> 
               <hi>Waldſmiedght,</hi> &amp;c. but this one is, I think, ſufficient.</p>
            <p>From this Doctrine may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Conſolation be afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to People labouring under the Stone in the Kidneys and Bladder; and Induſtrious Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians need not deſpair of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out ſuch Medicines as will Diſſolve or Break to pieces Stones contained in either of thoſe parts. One great reaſon I verily believe that has hindred Perſons from making diligent ſearch after ſuch Medicines, has been from a ſuppoſition, that ſcarce any Medicine could retain its Virtue, but muſt be in great meaſure or altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the many Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it muſt undergo, according
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135371:29"/> to the ordinary Laws of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumlocution; but were they fully ſatisfied (as there is no reaſon to the contrary) of this nearer Cut, I ſuppoſe people would not think the diſſolving Stones in the Kidneys and Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo difficult a Task as it hath hitherto been thought to be.</p>
            <p>To prove the Exiſtence of the foreſaid Paſſages for Fluid Subſtances from the Stomach, through the Veſſels of the Cawl to the Kidneys, and that Medicines may paſs unalter'd to the Kidneys and Bladder, I ſhall inſert a Couple of Caſes.</p>
            <p>One Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Tradeſman of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſent to me one Afternoon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring me to make all poſſible
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135371:30"/> haſte, for that he was upon the Wrack: When I came to him, I found him in a moſt dreadful condition, he not having made Water of two Days, and ſuch an intolerable Pain in his Back, that he was not able to ſupport himſelf under it. I preſently gave him ſome Medicines, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering him to take them in large quantities once in half an hour: In an hour and half's time, at furtheſt, he ſent to me to acquaint me that he was well, and at eaſe, having piſs'd two large Chamber-Pots full, which held at leaſt Two Quarts apiece, and in the firſt Pot-full above Two Large Spoonfuls of ſmall pieces of broken Stones. He ſeveral
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135371:30"/> times ſince, occaſioned by hard Drinking, has been under the ſame Circumſtances, and upon taking the ſame Medicines has found immediate Relief. Now had theſe Medicines been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed from the Stomach to the Small Guts, and from thence by the Lacteal Veſſels, the common Receptacle of the Chyle in the Meſentery, and ſo on to the Blood, and from thence be ſeparated by degrees in the Kidneys, as it is brought there by the Emulgent Arteries, it had been altogether impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Effect could have been ſo ſudden, and that the Medicines ſhould not have been greatly altered, or totally deſtroyed, by the many changes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135371:31"/> they muſt have undergone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could come to the Part affected. But by the way I have been ſpeaking of, the Medicines might all of them, and that without being in the leaſt impaired in their Virtue, be tranſmitted to the Part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and ſo perform their Operations in breaking to pieces the Stone or Stones they met with, either in the Kidneys or Bladder.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Wheatly,</hi> a Glaſier's Wife without <hi>Smithfield-Bars,</hi> had a long time been afflicted with the Stone in the Bladder, and for about Nine Months had confined her ſelf to her Chamber, the Miſery ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent being ſuch, that made
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135371:31"/> her altogether uncapable of any buſineſs; and of ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered ſhe was perfectly in deſpair, all common means having in vain been uſed; at laſt by ſome means or other ſhe was prevailed with to ſend for me: When I came to her, ſhe gave me a moſt lamentable Account of her Caſe; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I gave her all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement imaginable, yet all that I could ſay, made but little impreſſion upon her, ſhe ſuppoſing her Condition to be ſo deplorable, that to expect deliverance was vanity in the higheſt degree: However, ſhe was at laſt prevailed upon to try what I could do for her: I began to give her ſome Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135371:32"/> which ſhe took in large quantities, and repeated them once in four hours: It was upon a <hi>Monday</hi> morning ſhe began to take them, and on the <hi>Wedneſday</hi> night next following I exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her Water, and found ſome ſmall ragged Pieces of Stone in it; and taſting the Water, I could diſcern the Taſte of the Medicines, which were <hi>Salino-Sulphureous</hi> ones, to be as vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous altogether, as they were before ſhe had taken them into her Mouth, and not, as I could diſcern, in the leaſt altered in their taſte. On the Morrow Morning, being <hi>Thurſday,</hi> by Five a Clock ſhe ſent her Maid-Servant to me, to my Houſe in St. <hi>Martins-Lane,</hi> to acquaint
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135371:32"/> me that ſhe was delivered from her Miſery, and perfectly well. About Eight a Clock I went to viſit her, and found a Stone that ſhe had voided with little Pain, the Medicines having acted upon the Sphincter Muſcle of the Neck of the Bladder, and ſo relaxed it, as to make it give way for the Stone to paſs: The Length of the Stone was an Inch and half and half a quarter; it was Three Inches and a half round one way, and Two Inches and a half another. There were ſome ſmall flaws in it, which were made by thoſe little rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged pieces which came away the Night before, which I found in the Chamber-Pot.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135371:33"/> The thing was ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that it came to the Ears of her late Majeſty, who deſired to ſee the Stone, which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for Her, and ſhe was pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That it was the moſt Extraordinary Thing She had ever ſeen or heard of, to be brought away without Cutting or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Any one who doubts the Truth of this Relation, may yet ſee the Stone at Mrs. <hi>Wheatly</hi>'s, who carefully preſerves it: The extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Veracity and Integrity of the Perſon is ſuch, that I am ſure ſhe would not tell an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth to do any man ſervice.</p>
            <p>I could give ſeveral other Inſtances of this nature; but theſe Two are, I think, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135371:33"/> and a plain Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that there are Veſſels which carry Fluid Subſtances immediately from the Stomach to the Kidneys, without thoſe many Circumgyrations that people generally imagine: Nay, I don't queſtion but ſuddenly to make it appear by Ocular De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration; which if I could not do, to people who are not mere Scepticks, Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deduced from reiterated Experiments will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
            <p>I am ſure I have a great deal more to ſay for the Exiſtence of theſe Veſſels, than any of thoſe Learned Gentlemen who aſſert the Doctrine of Nutriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Nerves, have to ſay for that.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:135371:34"/>
            <p> The Learned and Ingenious Dr. <hi>Baynard</hi>'s Account he gives of the ſudden Effects of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar before-mentioned, in a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Suppreſſion of Urine, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a good Argument to evince the Truth of what I have been ſpeaking of. But to proceed to my Second Head, which is,</p>
            <p>That thoſe people who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with an Acidity in their Stomachs, are generally very Lean.</p>
            <p>To prove which Poſition, will be no very difficult Task; for the ſolid Food they eat (and generally they have good Appetites) which is that which affords moſt Nutrition, being over attenuated, is by that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135371:34"/> means made capable of paſſing through thoſe Veſſels I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned (which I ſhall preſume to call Urinary Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels) the more groſs parts on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being conveyed to the Small Guts, which having but few Nutritious Particles in them, can afford but very little Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment to the parts; and the parts being deſtitute of their uſual and neceſſary Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Leanneſs of conſequence follows.</p>
            <p>A ſufficient Argument to prove that Leanneſs proceeds from the want of a ſufficient quantity of <hi>Acid</hi> Subſtances in the Blood, is this: That Fat is nothing elſe but a Concrete, produced from the Mixture of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135371:35"/> the <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Oily</hi> Parts of the Blood: Now the Blood hath never any <hi>Acid</hi> in it, but when people are in a perfect ſtate of Health: And when at any time the Blood is deſtitute of <hi>Acid</hi> Particles, and abounds too much with <hi>Alkalious</hi> ones, (which argues a Morbid ſtate) as it doth in all thoſe people who have too great a quantity of <hi>Acid</hi> in their Stomachs, which upon experiment any man may find to be true, although at firſt ſight, I confeſs, it looks very like a Paradox. Now the Blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of <hi>Acid</hi> Particles to coagulate the Oily ones, there can be no freſh production of Fat, and that already generated having its <hi>Acid</hi> Particles morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135371:35"/> by the great quantity of <hi>Alkalious</hi> ones, preſently loſeth its conſiſtence, and is again converted into a thin Oyl, which is ſoon carried off by ſome of the Emunctories, there being nothing in the Blood fit for it to incorporate or mix with; and when theſe Oily Fat Particles are gone, then the Corroſive <hi>Alkalious</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles prey upon the Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, Nervous Fibres, and ſo cauſe general Diſorders; at other times when they are in great quantities thrown upon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular parts, according to the nature of the part affected, they cauſe different Diſeaſes: But I don't know any one Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe cauſed by <hi>Acids;</hi> unleſs it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135371:36"/> be over-much Fatneſs, and what we call the Heart-burn, if they are to be accounted Diſeaſes; the moſt Healthy People being ſubject to the Heart-burn: Tho' the Heart-burn is as often cured by <hi>Acids,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Ol. Vitriol. Dul.</hi> &amp;c. as by <hi>Alkalies:</hi> From whence I conjecture, that the Heart-burn alſo may be occaſioned from the Blood which is brought to the Coats of the Stomach, abounding with too great a quantity of <hi>Alkalious</hi> Corroſive Particles, which may vellicate and contract the part. Having in ſhort diſpatch'd this Head, I ſhall proceed to my Third;</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:135371:36"/>
            <p> That thoſe who abound with an Acidity in their Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs, are for the moſt part very Coſtive.</p>
            <p>From the ſame reaſon that people abounding with an Aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in their Stomachs, are Lean, it is that they are Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive alſo; the more Thin, Fluid Subſtances, being carried off by the Urinary Veſſels, and only the more Groſs ones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into the Guts, and for want of a ſufficient quantity of Moiſture, the Excrements are over-harden'd, and the Guts not ſufficiently lubricated; and therefore Coſtiveneſs muſt neceſſarily follow.</p>
            <p>But after all, I foreſee ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Objection will be raiſed;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135371:37"/> and therefore to make every body eaſy, I ſhall lay down the Objection, and endeavour to anſwer it.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="objection"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection:</hi> If the Acidity in the Stomach be the Cauſe of the ſolid Food we eat being over-attenuated, and ſo the Nutritious Particles being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off by the Urinary Veſſels, as in <hi>Atrophies,</hi> &amp;c. without being conveyed into the Blood, to afford Nutrition to the parts; How comes it to paſs that Iron or Steel, which you own to be an <hi>Acid,</hi> can be of any uſe? For inſtead of being uſeful, one would think that by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the Acidity, it ſhould exaſperate and increaſe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:135371:37"/>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="answer"/>
            <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer:</hi> I have before obſerved, that Iron or Steel cannot be conveyed into the Blood before it is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Vitriol; and therefore to thoſe people who have a great Acidity in their Stomachs, it is found abſolutely neceſſary to give Iron or Steel without any precedent Preparation; which has been long ſince taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by the Learned and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Dr. <hi>Cole,</hi> in his Phyſico-Medical Eſſay concerning the late Frequency of Apoplexies. Now Iron or Steel being given crude and unprepar'd, is by the means of the <hi>Acid</hi> in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach turned into a Vitriol, by which means the <hi>Acid</hi> is ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied, as to make it uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135371:38"/> of paſſing through the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt imperceptible Urinary Paſſages; and likewiſe by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodying the <hi>Acid,</hi> hinders it from over-much attenuating the Chyle; ſo that being mixed with the Chyle, they are toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conveyed into the Small Guts, and ſo on to the Blood, and by its Stiptick Acidity it confirms the Texture of the Blood, and mortifies the luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Alkalious Particles it meets with.</p>
            <p>As for what I mention con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Efficacy of Juice of Lemmons in immediately aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and taking off the violent Symptoms that attended a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who had been bitten with a Viper, after the Volatile Salt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135371:38"/> of Vipers, and other Antidotes, had in vain been given; I find the very ſame thing taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by <hi>Hoffman,</hi> in his <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Pharmaceutice Schroderi,</hi> pag. 444, 445.</p>
            <p>An Ingenious Perſon not long ſince, who had formerly embraced the Doctrine of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cids,</hi> was willing to try what Effects the Transfuſion of <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Alkalious</hi> Liquors into the Veins of Dogs would produce; accordingly he injected ſome <hi>Oyl of Sulphur per Campan.</hi> into the Veins of one Dog, which inſtead of diſordering him, made him brisk and lively, and very hungry: But another Dog into whoſe Veins ſome <hi>Oyl of Tartar per Deliquium</hi> (a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135371:39"/> known <hi>Alkaly)</hi> had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, it produced a clear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effect, the Dog being lumpiſh and dull, and in a few days died: But it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that theſe two Liquors were ſo diluted as to make them fit to be taken in at the mouth before they were inject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Something (as I remember) of the ſame nature, is alſo taken notice of by <hi>Fred. Hoffman, Fil. de Acido &amp; Viſcido.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been well aſſur'd from a Perſon of the Greateſt Honour, That the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> (who are the only Phyſicians there) adviſe their Patients, in times when the Plague rageth, to eat Lemon and Sugar, and to drink Lemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nade
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135371:39"/> in large quantities, and that by way of prevention; and thoſe people who do ſo, ſeldom or never have the Plague: And if at any time they are called to Perſons who have the Plague upon them, if they will but take the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Medicines in large quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they very rarely miſcarry.</p>
            <p>From many late Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I am fully convinced, that the Gout is without any great difficulty to be cured, or at leaſt a Fit to be taken off, in a ſmall time, by a proper Courſe of <hi>Acid</hi> Medicines, both internally taken, and externally applied to the Part affected, and that without the leaſt Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence afterwards: And I am
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135371:40"/> altogether certain, that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon why people have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſo fruſtraneouſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the Cure of the ſaid Diſtemper, has been from the general Prejudice they have had againſt <hi>Acid</hi> Medicines, which are the only things ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of doing ſervice.</p>
            <p>Tho I do ſo mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the Uſe of <hi>Acids</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in the Cure of Diſeaſes; yet I do not in the leaſt pretend that any one <hi>Acid</hi> is capable of anſwering a Phyſician's Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Cure of all Diſeaſes: Neither Vinegar nor Lemmons are to be reckoned <hi>Panacea's;</hi> tho, for ought I know, in the hands of a Perſon who well underſtands their uſe, they will
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135371:40"/> either of them do more than many of the celebrated <hi>Pana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man is fit to be called a Phyſician, who does not well underſtand the Nature of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and of the Juices con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a Human Body, which is what hath hitherto been but little enquired into; men taking up with general Notions that had no Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which has been the only reaſon that Phyſick hath been ſo long practiſed without the leaſt certainty; Phyſicians changing the Method of their Practice almoſt as often as we do that of our Cloaths. Being extremely well skill'd in the Anatomy of the Solid Parts, is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135371:41"/> a Noble Qualification, and enables a man to talk finely, but does not in the leaſt tend to enable men to cure Diſeaſes. It is an exact Skill in the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy of the Juices, the Fluid Parts, that will make a Man a good Phyſician: But in this ſort of Study few have been converſant. An exact Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Materia Medica</hi> in general, and the Specifick Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences there are between thoſe Medicines, ſeemingly of the ſame Tribe, is alſo an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For that <hi>Acid</hi> that will cure a Fever, will not cure the Gout; and that which will cure the Gout, will not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, cure another Chronical
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135371:41"/> Diſtemper; there being a vaſtly wide difference between thoſe very Medicines which are ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly the ſame.</p>
            <p>I do poſitively affirm, That neither Blood nor its Serum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any way expoſed to Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, will by that means in the leaſt become <hi>Acid,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more <hi>Alkalious:</hi> Now <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cids</hi> in general hindring Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and likewiſe reducing things from a ſtate of Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction that are already become Putrid, muſt be the great Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to cure Diſeaſes; for there is no Diſeaſe but what proceeds from ſome ſort of Putrefaction of the Fluid Parts of our Bodies.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:135371:42"/>
            <p> What I have ſaid in my Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and alſo in this Appendix, has been only in general terms; but I am now reducing all to a Method, I deſigning my Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Blood to be alſo a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical Hiſtory of Diſeaſes, with an Account of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines proper to be uſed in the Cure of them: I being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſerve my Generation to the utmoſt of my Power, let my Treatment be what it will.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix with Two or Three Caſes, and the Method I uſed in the Cure of them, as a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Truth of what I have ſaid concerning ſome things in my Eſſay.</p>
            <div n="1" type="case">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:135371:42"/>
               <head>Caſe the Firſt.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman who had long laboured under a Sciatica, <hi>viz.</hi> Two or Three Years, and had applied himſelf to ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the greateſt Eminence for Advice, and had by their Preſcriptions been loaded for that whole time with <hi>Alkalious</hi> Medicines, without receiving the leaſt advantage, the Leg and Thigh of the Left Side being greatly Emaciated, and a very large Glandulous Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor on his Hip: He was never free from violent Pain, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Lame. I firſt of all Purged him well for about a Fortnight with <hi>Calamel. Tart. Vitriolat.</hi> and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135371:43"/> 
                  <hi>Rezin of Jallap:</hi> I afterwards gave him the following Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which he took conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Three Times a Day for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Ten Weeks; in which time, without any External Application at all, his Pain left him, the Tumor diſappeared, and his Leg and Thigh, which were before waſted to mere Skin and Bones, became equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Plump and Fleſhy with the other.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Recipe <hi>Cinnaberis Antimonii, vel (quod melior eſt) Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii Com. Officinarum Recenter Levigat. Unciam Unam. Gum. Guaiaci Dracmas Sex. Conſ. Cynosbati Uncias Tres. Syr. Sambuci q. ſ. F. Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarium.</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:135371:43"/> 
                     <hi>Doſis eſt quant. Nuciſmoſcatae Ter in Die, Horis Medicinalibus, ſuper bibendo Uncias Octo Infuſi ſequentis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Recipe <hi>Rad. Bardanae Siccat. &amp; groſsè Contuſ. Uncias Octo. Baccar. Juniperi, Uncias Quatuor, ſem. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danae, Faxini ana Unciam Unam ſemis. Saſſafras Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam Unam. Tartari Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triolati Dracmas Tres. Aq. Font. Libras Sex. Infundè Clausè &amp; Calidè per horas</hi> xii. <hi>&amp; Coletur, Colaturae ſing. Libris duabus. Adde Sp. Liq. Guaiaci Rect. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam Semis M.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:135371:44"/>
               <p> This Method I have ſo often experienced in this Caſe, that I dare recommend it as to be depended upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="case">
               <head>Caſe the Second.</head>
               <p>A pretty young <hi>Gentleman,</hi> who had been too free with the Fair Sex, by his over-fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Embraces was Poxt to the higheſt degree, being Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous from the Crown of his Head to the Soles of his Feet, and all other Symptoms of the moſt confirmed Pox I ever met with. He was altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to <hi>Salivation,</hi> I therefore gave him the aforeſaid Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which he took three times a day for about two months;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135371:44"/> but I firſt of all purg'd him very well with <hi>Calamel. Tart. Vit.</hi> and <hi>Rezin. Jallap.</hi> and for the laſt Fortnight ſent him to the <hi>Bagnio</hi> three times a week, ordering him to take a large Doſe of the Electuary and Infuſion about an hour before he went into the <hi>Bagnio.</hi> At the two months end he was perfectly freed from his Leproſy, and his Skin as clean and white as ever I ſaw any one in my life; and all other Symptoms that attended him, were perfectly vaniſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="case">
               <head>Caſe the Third.</head>
               <p>A Corporal in the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s Regiment, was Poxed to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135371:45"/> the higheſt degree, upon which he applied himſelf to a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian near <hi>Chelſey,</hi> who put him into the powdering Tub of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction three times; and altho he had each time undergone a Regular <hi>Salivation,</hi> his Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms were not in the leaſt abated. He was emaciated to ſuch a degree, that he was like a meer <hi>Skeleton.</hi> He had vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Pain in his Head, Shoulders, Arms, Thighs, and Shin bones; and when he was warm in his Bed, the Pain was ſo exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that altho he was ſo weak as to be ſcarce able to ſtand, yet out of his Bed he was forced to get, and crawl about in the cold, which afforded him ſome ſmall Relief; his Appetite was
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135371:45"/> quite loſt, and a continual Hectick upon him. To be ſhort, I think I never ſaw ſo miſerable a Spectacle in my whole life. To this Man I gave the Electuary and Infuſion three times a day, which ſoon abated the violence of the Symptoms, and continuing the uſe of them about three months, altho he had ſeldom leſs than four or five Stools a day, yet he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd Fleſh, and in that time became a hale, hearty Man, to the great ſurprize of all who knew him. I may be poſitive that it was not above ſix weeks before he was able to walk about his buſineſs.</p>
               <p>I have given theſe very Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to I believe Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135371:46"/> People in ſeveral Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſtempers, with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſucceſs; and altho in the day time they ſeldom fail of working three or four times by Stool, and in the night provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Sweat; yet I have ſcarce known any one perſon who has taken them, that during the very time they are taking them, for all the very great Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they cauſe, that have not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly gather'd fleſh, and if weak, recover'd ſtrength. Whereas let the ſtrongeſt perſon take any of the common Purgers but a month together, and altho they have not above two or three Stools a day, yet they will emaciate them, and weaken them to a great degree, which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135371:46"/> is a very great Argument of the excellency of <hi>Cinnaberine</hi> Medicines mixt with <hi>Gum Guai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aci</hi> above the common Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: The one carrying off the Nutritious Juices, as well as the Excrementitious ones; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only cauſing a due Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Noxious, Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious Juices, which by ſo doing, Nature is thereby rid of any Load wherewith ſhe is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and enabled to apply the Nutritious Juices to the ends they are deſigned for.</p>
               <p>I have in ſome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Caſes, given above a pound of <hi>Cinnaber</hi> at times to one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and never knew the leaſt ill Symptom follow, nor ever once to excite <hi>Salivation.</hi> And I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135371:47"/> do verily believe, that in the hands of a perſon who knows how to uſe it, it is one of the greateſt Medicines in Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſeaſes in the World; but being uſed with <hi>Gum Guaiaci,</hi> and <hi>Spiritus Guaiaci Rect.</hi> it does much better than alone, they greatly aſſiſting it in its opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Being mixed with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cephalicks, and taken for ſome time, it is a wonderful Medicine in Epilepſies, and ſome other Nervous Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. <hi>Hoffman</hi> has wrote a whole Treatiſe of <hi>Cinnaber;</hi> and I am capable of ſpeaking ten times more in its praiſe from my own Experience, than <hi>Hoffman</hi> hath done.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:135371:47"/>
               <p> Convulſions are Diſtempers that Children are frequently troubled with, more of them dying of Convulſions than of all other Diſtempers, Teſtace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Powders are the Medicines generally given, as the great <hi>Aſylum</hi> to which Phyſicians fly, but very rarely with Succeſs. But upon the giving them tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>Acids,</hi> I have generally found them to anſwer my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
               <p>I was, not long ſince, ſent for to a Child who had Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions to ſuch a degree, that his Parents believed it to be an Epilepſy. His Belly was hard like a ſtone, and continual Tortions and Convulſive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions, ſometimes of his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135371:48"/> Hands and Arms, ſometimes his Legs and Thighs would be diſtorted and almoſt put out of Joint; ſometimes had the moſt violent Vomitings, at other times the Muſcles of his Face would be ſtrangely contracted. I gave it the following Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and in about two days he was perfectly free from his Convulſions.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Recipe <hi>Tart. Vitriolati Drac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Unam. Crem. Tart. Dracmas Duas. Caſtorei Dracm. Semis. Sacchari Albi Unciam. Sem. M. F. Pul. in</hi> viii <hi>Chartis diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buend. ex quibus cap. no</hi> 1. <hi>quartâ quâque horâ in Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lear. Julap. ſeq. ſuper bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:135371:48"/> 
                     <hi>Cochlear. Tria vel quatuor ejuſd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Recipe <hi>Aq. Roriſmarini, Pulegii ana Uncias Tres. Peon. Comp. Uncias Duas. Ol-Vitrioli Dul. Scrupul. Unam. Syr. Peoniae Dracmas Tres M. F. Julap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Recipe <hi>Ol. Amigdala. Amar. Unciam Unam. Ung. Dial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theae Uncias Duas. Ol. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſi, Pulegii ana gut.</hi> vi. <hi>m. F. Linimentum, cum quo Illinatur Regio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> Umbel. liculem Manè &amp; Veſperi, Superponendo Pannum La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum ter duplicatum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:135371:49"/>
               <p> By this Method, with ſome variation according as different Symptoms appear, I have known multitudes of Children, whoſe Lives have been deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, cured of the moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Convulſions in a ſmall time.</p>
               <p>I have likewiſe obſerved, that in malignant Fevers, thoſe people who are treated accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the uſual cuſtom, with <hi>Alkalies</hi> and <hi>Alexipharmicks,</hi> are generally attended with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Convulſions: But thoſe who uſe <hi>Acids</hi> plentifully, are ſeldom or never Convulſive.</p>
               <p>I have cured abundance of people of that troubleſome Cough that hath raged this <hi>March,</hi> by only giving them
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135371:49"/> large quantities of Lemmon and Sugar, to be eaten both day and night, and giving an Opiat with ſome Drops of <hi>Oyl of Sulphur per Campan.</hi> at night going to Bed.</p>
               <p>In violent Hyſterical Fits in Women, I have frequently, without (ſeldom) failing of Succeſs, given a Mixture of Two or Three Spoonfuls of Vinegar, a few Grains of <hi>Caſtor,</hi> and about a Quarter of a Pint of Spring Water: Which Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has frequently abated and taken off the Fits, when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had been greatly exaſperated by Spirit of <hi>Harts-horn, Sal Armoniac,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gas Sulphuris</hi> alſo given alone is a wonderful Medicine in violent
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135371:50"/> Hyſterical Fits. And in the beginning of Conſumptions, I believe there is not a better Medicine than <hi>Gas Sulphuris</hi> given in large quantities. But the <hi>Cortex,</hi> which is now ſo univerſally uſed in Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without the leaſt ſhew of Reaſon, I believe to be the moſt pernicious Medicine in Hecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſtempers that ever was given. I have enquired lately of ſeveral Perſons, both Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians and Apothecaries, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ever yet ſaw a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick cured by the <hi>Cortex,</hi> who have unanimouſly declared they never did, and that ſcarce any one that hath taken it, but have died. I muſt declare that I never yet ſaw any one
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135371:50"/> cured of a Conſumption, but by <hi>Acids,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Gas Sulphuris, Ol. Sulphuris per Campan.</hi> &amp;c. by the means of which I my ſelf have cured many. But ſometimes, in ſome very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Caſes, eſpecially if the Diſtemper have been of long ſtanding, and the Texture of the Lungs much ſpoiled, even <hi>Acids</hi> themſelves will leave us in the Lurch, even after Symptoms have ſeemed to be much abated, and things have look'd with a promiſing Aſpect. Which I my ſelf have in one or two Patients whoſe Lives have been very dear unto me, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced; which I cannot mention without the greateſt Concern. For all which, I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135371:51"/> dare not, even in Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, leave off the uſe of <hi>Acids,</hi> becauſe I am ſure they will do more than any other beſides; and there are no Medicines whatſoever that will make people Immortal. I have my ſelf cured many with <hi>Acids,</hi> but never could yet ſee or hear of one that was ever cured without them.</p>
               <p>The Learned Dr. <hi>Jones,</hi> whoſe Civility to me (tho an utter Stranger, whom I never ſaw) I cannot ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs; in a very kind and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Letter has ſent me a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Diſtempers he has in the Courſe of his Practice cured by Acids.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Hard Bellies in Children
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135371:51"/> with an Atrophy attending it, which is very common, and ſeldom cur'd by other Methods.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The Stone, that is, to take it off (if of a paſſable Bigneſs) with Eaſe, Speed, and Safety.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Child<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>bed Fevers, of which Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> ſays, they are moſt difficult to be cur'd of any.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Catarrh or Defluxion.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) <hi>Cholera Morbus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">(6.) Diarrhea and Dyſentery.</p>
               <p n="7">(7.) Jaundice.</p>
               <p n="8">(8.) The Small-Pox, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Worthy Perſon, whoſe Name is deſervedly famous throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> for his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Piece <hi>De Febribus Intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentibus,</hi> thus concludes; <hi>I would have ſent you more, but theſe coming readily to my mind, have been cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:135371:52"/> 
                  <hi>cured by me, by the means of Acids.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The wonderful Succeſs Dr. <hi>Baynard</hi> (whoſe intimate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation I have of late been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with) has had through the Courſe of his Practice, is eminently known both in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Bath,</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> where he formerly dwelt: And his Practice has chiefly run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Acids;</hi> which (as he hath all the reaſon in the world) he does ſtrenuouſly vindicate and defend; and by whom, I muſt own, ſince my Acquaintance with him, I have had clearer Notions of the different ſorts and various uſe of <hi>Acids</hi> than ever I knew before; he being one of the moſt Candid, Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135371:52"/> Communicable Perſons, I ever met with.</p>
               <p>It was out of a Life ſaving Principle, that theſe Gentlemen embraced this Doctrine of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cids,</hi> in oppoſition to the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; who for want of this knowledge, daily record their ſad Cures in <hi>Sextons</hi> Books and the Weekly Bills: And I dare ſay, they have wrought more Subſtantial, Good Cures, than any Twenty beſides them, who have acted upon different Principles.</p>
               <p>I don't find that the Method of making the <hi>Gas Sulphuris,</hi> which I have often mentioned, is any where ſet down; I ſhall therefore give an Account of its Preparation, which tho a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135371:53"/> very eaſy one, is for all that a very Noble Medicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Gas Sulphuris.</head>
               <p>Put into a large Glaſs Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that will hold Six or Eight Gallons, about Four Quarts of pure Spring Water; when you have ſo done, burn in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver a Quarter of a Pound of pure <hi>Sulphur Vivum</hi> made into Matches: You muſt take care that your Matches be very long, ſo that when they are lighted, the Flame may be as near the middle of the Body of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver as may be: By that time you have burnt Three or Four Matches, the Receiver will be ſo full of the Steams of Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, that when the lighted Match is put into it, it will be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135371:53"/> immediately extinguiſh'd; you muſt then ſtop the Mouth of the Receiver very exactly with a Wet Cloth, and let the Steams condenſe; when you ſee the Receiver clear, then burn more Matches till the Receiver is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain fill'd with Steams, then ſtop up again, and repeat this work till your Matches are all burnt, and your Water will then be impregnated with the Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Acid Steams of Brimſtone.</p>
               <p>This Medicine given liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Malignant Fevers has done Wonders, even where people have been given over as dead. It is an excellent Medicine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken by way of Prevention in Infectious Seaſons. And I think, if any Medicine deſerves
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135371:54"/> that Name, this doth deſerve to be called the true <hi>Prophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacticon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Baynard</hi> has another way of making the <hi>Gas Sulphuris</hi> ſomewhat more warm and Alexipharmick.</p>
               <p>Take a large Glaſs Receiver with a mouth of three or four Inches Diameter, place it Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizontally, into which pour <hi>Aq. Petaſitid. Ulmariae ſimp. Vini Rhenani, ana Libras duas Aq. Rutae, ſucci Pomorum ſilveſt. vet. ana Libram unam Aq. Theriacalis, Prophylact. Sylvij ana Uncias qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor M.</hi> Then take an Iron Ladle fitted to the mouth of the Glaſs, with a long Handle, put into the Ladle half an Ounce of <hi>Sulphur Vivum</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135371:54"/> accend with a ſmall Gad of red hot Steel, when lighted, clap it into the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver ſo far, that the Fumes may ariſe in the middle of the Glaſs, and the bigger the Glaſs the better; for the more Fumes it contains, the ſooner will your Operation be over. Stop the mouth with a wet Cloth, that the Steams get not out; when the Fumes have extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed the Flame, let it ſtand, that the <hi>Oleum Sulphuris</hi> may tric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle down the ſides of the Glaſs, and ſubſide upon the <hi>Menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> when the Fumes are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the Glaſs clear, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly draw out your Ladle, and repeat the Action, until it be well impregnated with ſtrong
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135371:55"/> Volatile <hi>Gas.</hi> Remember al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to keep the mouth of the Glaſs well ſtopped with the wet Cloth, otherwiſe the <hi>Gas,</hi> which is of a moſt ſubtile na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will evaporate.</p>
               <p>A Spoonful of this given once in two or three hours, in any proper Julap, doth moſt wonderfully extinguiſh Thirſt in Fevers, procure Sweat or Urine infallibly, takes off the drineſs of the Tongue, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates and cools the over-heated Bile, and procures Reſt. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo mixed with a little Claret-Wine, and a Drop or two of Oil of Cinnamon, does, to a Miracle, ſtop Vomiting, and the beſt Peptick for a weak and decayed Stomach.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:135371:55"/>
               <p> Note, That when the <hi>Gas</hi> is quite gone and flown off, the mixture will notwithſtanding remain ſowre, as impregnated with the <hi>Oleum Sulphuris;</hi> but the <hi>Gas,</hi> which is the better part, will in time be loſt, (it is ſo ſubtile) even almoſt through the pores of the Glaſs. You muſt dip the Cork-end of the Bottle in melted Brimſtone, and keep it always immerged in cold water. But the beſt way to keep it is in ſmall Glaſſes, and open no more at a time than you uſe, it loſing its vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile parts very much every time the Bottle in which it is kept is opened.</p>
               <p>As a further Illuſtration of the Doctrine of <hi>Acids,</hi> I ſhall
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135371:56"/> add an account I received from Dr. <hi>Oliver,</hi> one of the Phyſicians of the Fleet, about the uſe of <hi>Beveridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beveridge</hi> is a prickt, ſowr <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wine, one Hogſhead of this mixed with 3 Hogſheads of water, makes the Drink the Sailors are allowed to drink <hi>ad libitum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By my Experience in the Fleet, thoſe Ships Crews who drank this <hi>Acid</hi> Liquor for their common Drink, were much healtheir than thoſe who by their obſtinacy would not be brought to it; as for Example:</p>
               <p>The <hi>Royal Oak</hi> a third Rate, carrying about 500 men, whoſe Ship's Crew, by Admiral <hi>Nevil</hi>'s particular Order, began firſt to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135371:56"/> drink <hi>Beveridge,</hi> (he having had experience of it two years in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> in the <hi>Crown,</hi> in all which time he loſt not above two men), and in three months time I don't remember I had three Complaints, tho at the ſame time, in other Ships where they drank no <hi>Beveridge,</hi> Fevers and Fluxes were very frequent. Here I ſhall inſert one thing worthy of Note, That the <hi>Royal Oak</hi> wanting <hi>Beveridge,</hi> and being obliged to drink water only, in a few days time they grew very ſickly, and loſt above 30 men in a month, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the men themſelves were ſo ſenſible of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage they had by drinking <hi>Beve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge,</hi> that they heartily deſired
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135371:57"/> that they might drink nothing elſe but <hi>Beveridge,</hi> and begg'd it wherever they could find it. The like experience I had of the <hi>Eagle, Norfolk,</hi> and ſeveral other of our Ships, who were always better in health when they drank <hi>Beveridge,</hi> than when they drank Water alone, or found Wine and Water. From theſe Experiences, I adviſed the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of each reſpective Ship, to procure <hi>Beveridge</hi> for the common Drink of the men, and the Succeſs anſwered my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</p>
               <p>This is an exact Relation as I took it from Dr. <hi>Oliver</hi>'s own mouth.</p>
               <p>I have more to ſay, but have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready out-run the Bounds of an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix, and therefore ſhall omit what remains, for another opportunity.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:135371:57"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
